Promote the green transition.
What do the results of the state investments historically
and what happens to a society where the state is trying to control the economy
We are in the world front.
I address these questions in this week's video about "green planning economy".
I am not financed through colossal state credit guarantees, and are therefore entirely dependent on your voluntary donations.
If you appreciate my movies you help me therefore be able to continue making them
If you support me through any of the payment options below - then a big, big thank you to all of you who contribute
Today I talk about climate, capital and control.
come along
Planning economics is an economic system where the means of production is owned by the state
And where everything from prices to production goals is governed by a central planning authority.
This differs from market economy systems, where supply and demand are regulated by private companies and consumers.
The problem with centralizing financial decisions is that the decision -making burden quickly becomes impossible to manage,
which gradually leads to an increasing miscalling of capital.
Practically this means that a centralized authority simply cannot be able to predict
How many patches, millet clites and tractors that society will need during a five -year plan,
Something that was expressed with hair -raising clarity through the constant lack of basic goods of the former eastern states.
Because of this, the democratic states of the Western world rejected the planning of authoritarian socialism,
And instead built their prosperity in free markets that served free people.
However, the ambition to try to control the economy politically has in no way ceased
And today is expressed most clearly in connection with different types of climate initiatives.
Promote the green transition.
To reach this transition.
It is important to make this green transition.
And the whole transition that takes place in our society.
The transition in the transport sector.
The transition of the flight.
To succeed in the transition, everyone must pull in the same direction.
The notion that an ongoing climate crisis can only be resolved through large -scale, collective investments where "everyone pulls in the same direction"
This vision of the state as an economic client has
Unsurprisingly, very positively received by politicians and bureaucrats throughout the Western world.
In fact, the Swedish support authority Vinnova, whose task is to promote growth and sustainability in Sweden,
Very recently, a book entitled "Designing Mission" in fact is that the Swedish support authority Vinnova, whose task is to promote growth and sustainability in Sweden,
Very recently, a book entitled "Designing Mission" published
In which Mazzucato personally praises the authority's progressive initiative,
And besides, perform an equally surprising as speaking tribute to the million program!
“However, it is not every country that has a 'Vinnova' [...] Life here is permeated by the memory of the Million Program,
Zero tolerance target [...] and several decades of progressive social measures for justice. "
The book then continues to under the heading “Learning from the Million Program”
Compare Sweden's million programs with the moon landing:
“The assignment was largely successful, and 1,006,000 homes were built until 1974. [...]
The results of the million program are deserved to be seen in the same light as the Apollo program.
The housing policy terrain of social policy is just as complicated as space trips ”
Thus, for those who do not remember, the million program was the housing -based equivalent of Swedish social democracy
To Mao Tse Tung's "big leap".
However, large -scale government assignments of this type rarely produce the results that its architects hope for.
In China, the "big leap" resulted in starvation and economic collapse,
And in Sweden, the Million Program resulted in segregation, ghettone and aspiration
Because everyone who could afford avoided the Social Democrats' depressing new concrete complexes.
The social engineering or what to call it has, after all, in many people's eyes sentenced.
Yes.
... as very unsuccessful.
Is it the unsuccessful?
- Yes.
Almost actually it is very difficult to love.
In the article "How could it go so badly" from 1977, the Swedish master architect Sture Lindström summarized the Million Program in the following words:
“Instead, it became legislation, control and power to the politicians for almost the entire slant.
Result: A newly built slum of previously never seen scope.
A slum that, through its existence, also makes the planning and housing policy of the future a difficult swamp. "
That the Swedish innovation support authority Vinnova together with left -wing economist Mariana Mazzucato
Instead, chooses to highlight the million program as a great success
testifies to how this Great Statural Command ideology not only exaggerates the politically controlled missions what people actually want
but also about how to ignore what actually works.
For work, do virtually no state assignments at all.
The same year that the Million Program was completed, the Social Democrats initiated Sweden's largest industrial policy investment ever,
and invested the equivalent of SEK 12 billion in a colossal industrial policy project called “Steelverk 80”.
The assignment was to ten -level production of iron in Norrbotten to 1980, to increase the population by over 5000 inhabitants.
The then chairman of the Industry Committee Ingvar Svanberg justified the investment in the following words:
“I see this investment as extremely valuable to our entire country that we will be further refining such raw material as ore,
That we create employment opportunities and I see it as very valuable to Norrbotten. "
However, the initiative, which would have become a social democratic parade project, was canceled already after three years because the steel industry ended up in crisis
But before that, large parts of Luleå's city center had already been demolished and built several large -scale residential areas that were now empty.
In the book “Stålverk 80 Ekonomi & amp;
Politics ”summarizes the three researchers Erik Ruist, Ingemar Ståhl and Lars Wohlin
The criticism of the project in the following words:
“In fact, one cannot make any proper cost estimates before the procurement is completed
suggests an overly light -hearted approach to the need for calculations ”
“In the case of steel mills 80, financing is largely done with tax assets.
[...]
In this case, those who made the decision have very small pros and cons linked to the final financial outcome of the project. "
"In summary, we have found the profitability information presented in the bill to be extremely optimistic."
This is the typical outcome when investments are driven by the state.
In the early 2000s, billions were invested in Norrland to lead the world's climate change
through the production of the green fuel ethanol.
In 2006, a new law was driven through that forced all the sandwiches over a certain size to install pumps for ethanol,
Development of new brand new engine types was subsidized and in 2007 the environmental car premium came,
which also subsidized all purchases of ethanol cars with SEK 10,000.
The then Prime Minister Göran Persson motivated these billion initiatives with Sweden being a pioneering country.
Environmental cars are increasing sharply, we get a new infrastructure for this, it is produced in Sweden.
We develop new engines, we are in the world front.
And this is precisely this that we are ahead of others shows that a country can go ahead.
The state's generous support meant that the ethanol initiatives became increasingly feverish.
In just four years, the Swedish vehicle market went from 2 to 80 ethanol car types,
And in 2008, 20 percent of all newly registered vehicles in Sweden were adapted for ethanol operation.
A few years later, the ethanol project was silently phased out, since it was discovered that the ethanol simply did not keep the measure as a fuel.
This led to the demand for both ethanol and ethanol cars collapsed
with an overall calculated socio -economic cost of at least SEK 30 billion.
This is the typical outcome when investments are driven by the state.
It is important to emphasize that the questioning of today's state change initiatives
is not a criticism of sustainability work in itself, but only a questioning of the likelihood that the investments can achieve the goals that are hoped.
It is also important to remember that all of Sweden's failed investments have historically been motivated by exactly the same argument:
"We go ahead", "We create progressive new jobs" and "We create a profitable new super economy".
This place is at the very forefront of the green transition.
However, the cluster of investments that are currently being forced in the name of the transition will have all previous efforts to fade
For the assignments to simultaneously electrify Sweden with renewable energy sources,
to switch over to large -scale production and storage of hydrogen and switch to the manufacture of so -called green steel
is to such an extent that there are no comparable examples.
More and more, for example, the state attempts to force more wind power create great losses.
Already in 2020, the municipal -owned company Skellefteå Kraft was forced, for example, to write down over half a billion SEK in fixed assets
The Turbine Problems Would See Its Net Loss Rise More Than Sixfold in 2023.
When asked whether the wind farm is to be sold or closed down, Siemens Energy's CEO Christian Bruch replied
That you are currently "investigating all options, with very open eyes.
[Wind power is important but] it is of the utmost importance that the business is profitable,
Something that you failed in recent years. "
In a similar way, the disputed reduction obligation proved to be severely inflation -driven,
And also led to Sweden being forced to vacuum the world market on slaughterhouses
To put together the bioethanol that the dilution required.
At the same time, the cherished "green steel" still lacks basic energy supply,
And how the investment need of 150 to 400 billion is to be covered is unreported.
Neither does the politics expectations of hydrogen gas do not seem to be proportionate to what is physically possible.
More than 95 percent of the hydrogen used today is produced from fossil sources such as natural gas and oil
And producing green hydrogen through electrolysis requires between three and five times more energy.
Energy that is thus not even close to being able to be produced and in particular not with wind power.
Let me once again repeat: This is no criticism of either climate or sustainability work,
Without merely finding that government assignments, ambitions and climate goals do not change the underlying reality.
Of course, it is attractive for politicians to be able to present nominal action
By setting ambitious goals and then generously fertilizing these goals with honest people's tax money,
But this usually only means that the tax funds are abolished without the goals being achieved.
In addition, the state assignments are at risk of mistaken so large amounts of capital that competition is distorted
And companies adapt to get part of the support money instead of conducting real innovation work.
Because of this, the large government assignments not only risk wasting money,
Without also inhibiting the technological development that could have really helped to solve the climate problems.
This is exactly what caused Eastern Europe's planning economies to stagnate
For whatever command economists as Vinnova and Mazzucato consider,
So does not mean a decision on large -scale state -funded assignments that the goals are only achieved that the state chooses the way at the expense of all others.
For as an ancient Jewish proverb resigned states:
"Man plans but God laughs."
Especially when it comes to financial plans.
Want to know more about the problems with a mission -driven economy
May I recommend the book "Moonshots and the New Industrial Policy Questioning the Mission Economy".
This book provides historical examples of unsuccessful government initiatives worldwide.
Link to free download can be found in the video description